

Gregory Ditzler

Assistant Professor

Applied Machine Learning, Data Mining, Feature Subset Selection, Multiple Classifier Systems, & Data Science

I am an assistant professor at the University of Arizona in the Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering, and a member of the Cognitive Sensing, Processing, and Security Research Center.

Education

2011–2015 **PhD**, *Drexel University*, Electrical & Computer Engineering.

Advisor: Gail Rosen, Ph.D.

Research areas: feature subset selection, online learning, and knowledge discovery in the microbiome

2009–2011 MSc, Rowan University, Electrical & Computer Engineering.

Advisor: Robi Polikar, Ph.D.

Research areas: learning in nonstationary environments, imbalanced data, and change detection

2004–2008 BSc, Pennsylvania College of Technology, Electronics Engineering Technology.

Project: PowerPC and MicroBlaze applications on the Xilinx Virtex-II Pro

Minor: Mathematics

Employment

Current The University of Arizona, Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering, Tucson, AZ.

Assistant Professor 2015-Present

2011–2015 Drexel University, Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering, Philadelphia, PA.

Research Fellow 2011-2015 2011-2013

Teaching Assistant

2009–2015 Rowan University, Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering, Glassboro, NJ.

Adjunct Professor 2010-2015 2009-2011 Research Assistant

2013 AT&T Research Labs, Shannon Laboratory, Florham Park, NJ.

Research Intern (Technical II)

2007-2009 QorTek, Inc., Systems Engineering, Williamsport, PA.

> Electronic Systems Engineer 2008/09 Electronic Systems Intern 2007/08

Awards & Honors

- 2015 Joseph and Shirley Carleone Endowed Fellowship
- 2015 Drexel University's Office of Graduate Studies Research Excellence Award
- 2015 Best Poster at the Drexel IEEE Research Day Poster Competition
- 2014 IEEE SSCI 2014 Doctoral Consortium Travel Award

1230 E Speedway Blvd – ECE Bldg. – Tucson, AZ 85721 ⊠ ditzler@email.arizona.edu • '🗓 www2.engr.arizona.edu/ ditzler

- 2014 NSF Travel Award to the ACM International Workshop on Big Data in Life Sciences
- 2014 Best Student Paper at the International Joint Conference on Neural Networks
- 2014 IEEE Computational Intelligence Society Travel Award
- 2013 Nihat Bilgutay Research Award
- 2013 Koerner Family Engineering Research Award
- 2012 Defense Threat Reduction Agency & NSF Algorithms Workshop Travel Grant
- 2011 Student Travel Award for the IJCNN, National Science Foundation
- 2011 Graduate Research Achievement Award, Rowan University
- 2008 Award for Outstanding Leadership & Service to the Pennsylvania College of Technology IEEE Branch
- 2008 Penn College Award for Leadership to the College and Community

Professional Affiliations

2014-Present Association for Computing Machinery

2004-Present IEEE Member (Signal Processing Society, Computational Intelligence Society)

2014-Present Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics

Publications

In Preparation / Submitted / Under Revision

- **G. Ditzler**, R. Polikar, and G. Rosen, "A Sequential Learning Approach for Scaling up Filter-Based Feature Subset Selection," Under Review, 2015.
- **G. Ditzler**, J. LaBarck, J. Ritchie, G. Rosen, and R. Polikar, "Online Feature Selection Using Bagging and Boosting," Under Review, 2015.
- N. Bouaynaya, G. Ditzler, and R. Shterenberg, "AKRON: An Algorithm for Approximating Sparse Kernel Reconstruction using Convex Optimization," In Preparation, 2015.
- o **G. Ditzler**, "Spectral Estimation Learning in Nonstationary Environments," In Preparation, 2015.

Book Chapters

- C. Alippi, G. Boracchi, G. Ditzler, R. Polikar, and M. Roveri, "Adaptive Classifiers for Nonstationary Environments," *Contemporary Issues in Systems Science and Engineering*, IEEE/Wiley Press Book Series, M.-C. Zhou, H.-X. Li, and M. Weijnen (Eds), 2015.
- o J.-L. Bouchot, W. Trimble, **G. Ditzler**, Y. Lan, S. Essinger, and G. Rosen, "Advances in machine learning for processing and comparison of metagenomic data," *Computational Systems Biology*, In A. Kriete and R. Eils (Eds), Springer, 2014.
- **G. Ditzler**, Y. Lan, J.-L. Bouchot, and G. Rosen, "Feature selection for metagenomic data analysis," *Encyclopedia of Metagenomics*, K. E. Nelson (Eds), 2014.

Journals

- **G. Ditzler**, J. Calvin Morrison, Y. Lan, and G. Rosen, "Fizzy: Feature selection for metagenomics," BMC Bioinformatics, 2015, vol. 16, no. 358.
- **G. Ditzler**, M. Roveri, C. Alippi, and R. Polikar, "Adaptive strategies for learning in nonstationary environments: a survey," *IEEE Computational Intelligence Magazine*, 2015, vol. 10, no. 4, pp. 12–25.
- **G. Ditzler**, R. Polikar, and G. Rosen, "Multi-Layer and Recursive Neural Networks for Metagenomic Classification," *IEEE Transactions on Nanobioscience*, vol. 14, no. 6, 2015, pp. 608–616.
- o **G. Ditzler**, R. Polikar, and G. Rosen, "A bootstrap based Neyman-Pearson test for identifying variable importance," *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*, vol. 26, no. 4, 2015, pp. 880-886.
- G. Ditzler and R. Polikar, "Incremental learning of concept drift from streaming imbalanced data," in *IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering*, vol. 25, no. 10, 2013, pp. 2283–2301.

Conferences

- o **G. Ditzler**, M. Austen, R, Polikar, and G. Rosen, "Scaling a Neyman-Pearson Subset Selection Approach Via Heuristics for Mining Massive Data," 2014, *IEEE Symposium on Computational Intelligence and Data Mining*, 2014, Orlando, FL. (**travel award**)
- **G. Ditzler**, G. Rosen, and R. Polikar, "Domain Adaptation Bounds for Multiple Expert Systems Under Concept Drift," *International Joint Conference on Neural Networks*, 2014, Beijing, China. (travel award & best paper)
- G. Ditzler and G. Rosen, "Feature Subset Selection for Inferring Relative Importance of Taxonomy,"
 ACM International Workshop on Big Data in Life Sciences, 2014, Newport Beach, CA. (invited & travel award)
- **G. Ditzler**, G. Rosen, and R. Polikar, "Incremental learning of new classes with unbalanced data," *International Joint Conference on Neural Networks*, 2013, Dallas, TX.
- G. Ditzler, G. Rosen and R. Polikar, "Discounted expert weighting for concept drift," *International Symposium on Computational Intelligence in Dynamic and Uncertain Environments*, 2013, Singapore, pp. 61–67.
- o **G. Ditzler**, R. Polikar, and G. Rosen, "Information theoretic feature selection for high dimensional metagenomic data," in *IEEE International Workshop on Genomic Signal Processing and Statistics*, 2012, Washington, D.C., pp. 143–146.
- **G. Ditzler**, G. Rosen and R. Polikar, "A transductive learning algorithm for concept drift," in *International Joint Conference on Neural Networks*, 2012, Brisbane, Australia, pp. 945–952.
- **G. Ditzler**, R. Polikar and G. Rosen, "Determining significance in metagenomics," in *North Eastern Biomedical Engineering Conference*, 2012, Philadelphia, PA, pp. 385–386.
- G. Ditzler, R. Polikar, and G. Rosen, "Forensic identification with environmental samples," in International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing, 2012, Kyoto, Japan, pp. 1861–1864.
- G. Ditzler and R. Polikar, "Semi-supervised learning in nonstationary environments," in *International Joint Conference on Neural Networks*, 2011, San Jose, CA, pp. 2471–2478. (student travel award)
- G. Ditzler and R. Polikar, "Hellinger distance based drift detection algorithm," in *IEEE Symposium* on Computational Intelligence in Dynamic and Uncertain Environments, 2011, Paris, France, pp. 41–48.
- **G. Ditzler**, J. Ethridge, R. Polikar, and R. Ramachandran, "Fusion methods for boosting performance of speaker identification systems," in *Asia Pacific Conference of Circuits and Systems*, 2010, Kuala Lampur, Malaysia, pp. 116–119.
- G. Ditzler, R. Polikar, and N. V. Chawla, "An incremental learning algorithm for nonstationary environments and imbalanced data," in *International Conference on Pattern Recognition*, 2010, Istanbul, Turkey, pp. 2997–3000.
- o J. Ethridge, **G. Ditzler**, and R. Polikar, "Optimal ν -SVM parameter estimation using multiobjective evolutionary algorithms," in *IEEE Congress on Evolutionary Computing*, 2010, Barcelona, Spain, pp. 3570–3577.
- G. Ditzler and R. Polikar, "An incremental learning framework for concept drift and class imbalance." in *International Joint Conference on Neural Networks*, 2010, Barcelona, Spain, pp. 736-743.
- o **G. Ditzler**, M. Muhlbaier, and R. Polikar, "Incremental learning of new classes in unbalanced data: Learn⁺⁺.UDNC," in *International Workshop on Multiple Classifier Systems*, 2010, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, N. El. Gayer *et al*, vol. 5997, Cairo, Egypt, pp. 33–42.

Invited Talks

- G. Ditzler, "Scalable machine learning and its applications to life science," University of Arizona, Dept. of SIE, Tucson, AZ, 2015.
- **G. Ditzler**, "Scalable machine learning and its applications to life science," *University of Arizona*, Dept. of ECE, Tucson, AZ, 2015.
- G. Boracchi and **G. Ditzler**, "An introduction to learning in nonstationary environments," *IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence*, South Africa, 2015.

- **G. Ditzler**, "An introduction to MapReduce," *Drexel University's Center Biological Discovery from Big Data*, Philadelphia, PA, 2015.
- **G. Ditzler**, "Scalable machine learning for knowledge discovery and prediction," *University of Arizona*, Tucson, AZ, 2014.
- G. Ditzler, "Scalable machine learning for knowledge discovery and prediction," Rowan University, Glassboro, NJ, 2014.
- **G. Ditzler**, "Feature Subset Selection for Inferring Relative Importance of Taxonomy," *ACM International Workshop on Big Data in Life Sciences*, Newport Beach, CA, 2014.
- **G. Ditzler**, "Generic language modeling using deep neural networks," *AT&T Shannon Research Labs*, Florham Park, NJ, August 2013.
- **G. Ditzler**, "Functional feature selection over varying sample phenotypes: Integration of feature selection methods into KBase," *Genomic Science Annual Contractor-Grantee Meeting/USDA-DOE Plant Feedstock Genomics for Bioenergy*, Washington, DC, November 2013.

Other: Workshops, Theses, and Non-Peer Reviewed Abstracts

- G. Ditzler and G. Rosen, "Scalable Subset Selection Using Filters and its Applications," DTRA/NSF Algorithms Workshop, Arlington, VA, 2015.
- **G. Ditzler**, "Scalable Subset Selection Using Filters and its Applications," *PhD Thesis*, Drexel University, 2015.
- G. Ditzler, "Scaling Up Subset Selection and the Microbiome," IEEE SSCI Doctoral Consortium, Orlando, FL, 2014.
- G. Ditzler, J. Calvin Morrison, and G. Rosen, "FizzyQIIME: Feature Selection for Metagenomics," Genomic Science Annual Contractor-Grantee Meeting/USDA-DOE Plant Feedstock Genomics for Bioenergy, Bethesda, MD, 2014.
- G. Ditzler, R. Polikar, and G. Rosen, "Application of a post-hoc Neyman-Pearson hypothesis test for identifying variable importance in comparative metagenomics," DTRA/NSF/NGA Algorithms Workshop, Boulder, CO, 2014.
- J.-L. Bouchot, G. Ditzler, and G. Rosen, "The Earth Microbiome Project from a Data Science Perspective", DTRA / NSF / NGA Algorithms Workshop, Boulder, CO, 2014.
- **G. Ditzler**, Y. Lan, and G. Rosen, "Functional feature selection over varying sample phenotypes: Integration of feature selection methods into KBase," *Genomic Science Annual Contractor-Grantee Meeting/USDA-DOE Plant Feedstock Genomics for Bioenergy*, Bethesda, MD, 2013.
- G. Ditzler and G. Rosen, "Deep Learning of Features and Structure of Soil Samples," DTRA/NSF/NGA Algorithms Workshop, San Diego, CA, 2012. (travel award)
- **G. Ditzler**, "Incremental Learning of Concept Drift from Imbalanced Data," *Master's Thesis*, Rowan University, 2011.

Teaching Experience

Graduate

• ECE-541a: Automatic Control F2015

The University of Arizona

Undergraduate

ECE-175: Computer Programming For Engineering Applications
 Sp2016

The University of Arizona

• ECE-441a: Automatic Control F2015

The University of Arizona

 ENGR-01401: Jr./Sr. Engineering Clinic F2013, Sp2014, F2014, Sp2015 Rowan University

o ECE-09202: Networks II

Rowan University

F2010

Activities

Journal Reviewer

- BMC Bioinformatics
- BMC Genomics
- Elsevier Neurocomputing
- o IEEE Computational Intelligence Magazine
- o IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics
- o IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering
- o IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics: Part B
- o IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems
- o Springer Neural Computing & Applications Journal
- Springer Neural Processing Letters Journal
- o Springer Pattern Analysis & Applications Journal

Conference Organizer

 IJCNN: Special Session of Concept Drift, Domain Adaptation and Learning in Nonstationary Environments

Conference Reviewer

 Artificial Intelligence Applications and Innovations Conference 	2013
 IEEE International Joint Conference on Neural Networks 	2011-15
o IEEE International Symposium of Circuits & Systems	2011

- o IEEE Symposium on Computational Intelligence in Dynamic & Uncertain Environments 2013-15
- International Workshop on Learning Strategies and Data Processing in Nonstationary Environments 2013

Technical Program Committee Member

 ACM International Workshop on Big Data in Life Sciences 	2015
o IEEE/INNS International Joint Conference on Neural Networks	2014/15
o IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence	2013–15
 International Conference on Contemporary Computing (IC3) 	2015

University of Arizona Service

UA Instructional Equipment and Software Planning Committee
 2015/16

Other Service

 Drexel IEEE Graduate Forum Board Member (Vice President) 	2013/14
IEEE Region 2 Student Activities Conference Planning Committee	2008
O Penn College IEEE Branch Vice Chair	2007/8

Advising

PhD

• Heng Liu (2015-Present), The University of Arizona (ECE)

Committees Served

PhD

• Matthew Bunting (2015), The University of Arizona (ECE)